When you mentioned the word dark factory, it's like blasphemy, it won't work.
I think technically it will work, you're not organized around
The continuous learning is where the knowledge compounds
and that seems to be becoming the moat of a company.
Like how fast can you learn?
How fast can you adapt to a new idea?
How fast can you do it?
Like, even if that means rewriting the whole codebase, it doesn't matter.
But like, how fast can you get that?
And the people who contribute to that metric are the ones that are
really helping you on the journey, not token billionaires.
The AI Native Dev is a podcast for developers and engineering
leads at the cutting edge of AI and agentic coding.
Join your hosts, Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple,
every week as we chat with the most exciting voices in
AI and tackle the biggest questions facing developers today.
This is the AI Native Dev.
We just
wrapped up two amazing days at AI Native DevCon in London.
But the great thing is that
we get to do it all over again in New York City this November.
You're absolutely right.
We're going to be back in the city that never sleeps on November 3rd and
4th for more amazing sessions, really engaging hands-on workshops and much more.
Yeah, all that great networking, partying, eating and
drinking that you've come to expect from AI Native DevCon.
We think we have one of the best hallway tracks in the business,
and it's the perfect complement to our incredible speakers and presenters.
We'll both be in person and virtual,
with live streamed access to all mainstage keynotes and talks.
Sign up right now for our Super Blind Bird ticket for just $100.
Only available for a limited time.
We're really excited to be headed back to the Big Apple, and we hope
to see you all there.
Hello
and welcome to another episode of the AI Native Dev.
We're still here in San Francisco enjoying AI engineer.
And we've managed to grab Patrick Debois
a third or fourth time for the podcast.
Yeah. Regular and regular. Yeah, yeah.
So actually, I've talked to a number of people who have said
their favorite episodes are with Patrick Debois on the podcast, you know that.
Do you need something from us?
No, no, I'm just I'm just I'm just mentioning it.
Thank you. Observation.
Well, it's not it wasn't my compliment.
I prefer the Guy ones personally, but no, no that's fine.
So, Patrick, you are obviously
someone with a wealth of experience in a number of places.
Of course.
Should I mention DevOps?
The the stepbrother?
I think of DevOps, right?
And AI has really like AI's
really gripped you more than anything else that I've seen since.
Since the DevOps days and DevOps days I use as a
pun there in terms of the conference, the set of conferences
that you built, what is it about AI that that really grips you?
So much?
So I think I always taken one
new technology emerging, emerging.
And so that, you know, actually early on with the internet,
with cloud, kind of with kind of the collaboration
and then leading to DevOps and then cops and mobile.
So anytime there's something changing and I would say
I like kind of this emerging chaotic phase of a new technology,
but not just for the technology, but also kind of the impact
on the organization and the way we were like.
And that's kind of the typical narrative
within DevOps is the socio-technical kind of ecosystem. Yes.
And I kind of had a hunch that this AI thing was like automation
kind of blowing doors of kind of the ways that we were working.
And that's kind of been, you know, captivating around it.
And one of the things that you've done time and time again, with these kind
of major shifts in the industry is the kind of like deep thinking
and understanding of what needs to change and how it needs to change.
Obviously, there are a lot of these changes
for cloud, for DevOps and these these types of,
you know, motions that that we've experienced
with agentic development
with, with AI generally exactly the same has happened.
And you've done a bunch of research work to to try and help people understand
not just the the technical challenges and changes they need to make,
but also the process changes, the organizational changes.
And in fact, that's what you're speaking about at AI engineer.
Tell us a little bit about your talk that you're giving tomorrow.
Yeah.
So every new technology will have the impact in the org.
And I feel right now a little bit of the technology.
I'm not saying it's maturing because that's a broad overstatement,
but we kind of get a sense of direction now within AI coding how it's going
from context to harness to loop to, you know,
what is mentioned, loop craft loops of loops and, and so on.
So the technicalities are improving.
And what you're not seeing in the org is the shift to
what does that mean for developer on day to day.
And that's kind of one way. And that's often talked about.
But what does it mean
for a team and a team leader to kind of deal with that change.
Like maybe like one of the is well, if your team gets more performant,
are you running dry on requirements?
And can people who depend on you for the marketing and the sales?
If you have 100 features a day?
How do they package this to their end user?
So there's an impact on.
The team without massively confusing them every week or.
So you have that on a team.
I can see that already a little bit
like happening maybe more in a shared component,
like a platform team who's kind of taking their like the
if the loop of loops evaluates to a harness and that becomes
more of a factory, is that reusable across teams?
It's that of each team doing their own reusable components.
So their life is changing.
What do they need to provide for kind of the new developers
and the new teams doing the work?
And then the VP of engineering kind of how do they kind of structure
the org around that?
So for me, level zero
technical agent enablement, this is the whole conference, right?
Team enablement,
platform enablement and kind of making sure your organization is enablement.
I think those are like not enough talked on.
But it's also because the one is changing so often
that we have all their narratives in all the other layers.
And that's kind of where I want to bring the stories out.
And it's really interesting that when you talk about
you kind of mentioned the word maturity there,
and it's like, where are we on this maturity curve?
Because, you know, for me looking at it, there is no maturity
because every single time we try and get used to something,
there's something else that changes,
whether it's prompts that we need to start looking at,
then it's context, then it's harness is, then it's loop engineering.
And it's like every single time where we think we know
what is the area that we need to spend time on and do research around.
There's always something around the corner.
So when we look at maturity,
are we just in a continuous exploration and continuous change,
or do you feel like there are things which we can longer term say, hey,
these are things that we need to really focus more on to actually get more mature
practices and processes that we expect to keep a long time
or as teams do, we need to actually build that muscle,
which is more about continuous change and how do we continue to adapt?
What would you say the the goals are for teams in that respect?
So I think there is a settling in like
yes prompts and specifications will be a keeper.
Yes harnesses and context will make sense.
The loops will be so.
I don't think this is changing all the time.
It is adding on top of kind of the the stack that is building.
And I think that's quite common in these emerging times where you're saying
like, oh, this was the first slice and that was revolutionary.
And then the bill on top of that, and that is kind of like building more
and more, I think.
I don't know what we, you know, technically in the code generation,
if you have teams of agents building the whole thing,
then then kind of that is already one way of kind
of solving the coding thing where we might now see things is,
but how do we prove that the agent in the right thing.
So something that we've been so focused on, the generation will move
the bottleneck over there,
or how can we assess the risk of things that are coming in?
So as the craft matures, it's normal that you feel a little bit lost,
because every time there's a little bit of a different attention level.
But I think it's the industry maturing as what is
actually the the way the technology kind of works.
Now, that's a different thing from an organizational maturity level,
which might not be in the known of the latest,
which could be like still working in the old kind of version of completion
and thing.
It doesn't work for me and making bad decisions on on this.
And that's kind of a challenge in that transient period of
while the the stack is maturing now, will it keep evolving?
The rate has been astounding.
That just kind of change over change.
But you can also see some it's not it wasn't unpredictable.
That will reach in kind of the an agent loop agents of agents.
That was kind of predictable.
But you need the industry to start building that layer out
so it becomes accessible for most of the people instead of having to do everything.
Yeah, but that's the race that we're in is keeping up.
And for some that is keeping up the competitive advantage,
like almost being in the edge where other is, it's more like, yeah,
you know, we want to work the new way, but like we're not that fast.
We don't have the risk or we have a lot more things around there.
So why would you say kind of like average organizations are in terms of maturity?
Are we are we toddlers?
Are we stages of puberty?
Maybe. What would you say we are.
We're I think on average, but not that high in a big org because
the, the friction of scaling things in org are different than doing it on a solo.
Or maybe in a team of five there's stakeholders.
There's like processes in place that will kind of cause that.
So I think it's normal that an enterprise is kind of slower.
Now the typical pattern there is, they might have one team
is kind of like leading the charge.
And then that becomes like multiple teams.
And then they kind of work on the friction and overcome it.
When maybe
with the comparison of DevOps, when they said,
well, continuous delivery, that doesn't work for us.
It was basically they were saying, we're not ready yet.
It wasn't that the tech was impossible for them to use, but the org wasn't ready.
And I think when you mentioned the word dark factory, it's like blasphemy, right?
Like similarly like it won't work.
I think technically it will work, but you're not organized around this.
So yeah. Super interesting.
Now, I'd love to talk about a new
initiative that you that you've built up over over
the recent months called the patterns, AI patterns.
And folks can take a look at Tessl.io forward slash patterns.
Now, this was a little research project that you built.
And I'd love to actually maybe begin
by talking about how you actually built up all the information that's here.
First of all, tell us what is the what is the pattern site?
So as the change of the industry is faster
and faster, what you typically have is a fragmentation of kind of news.
And there's a fire hose of news and things that are changing.
And there's the old information, there's the new information. So
my job
is to listen into the emerging things that are happening
and also understand how it's like stabilizing as a thing.
So the way that I would normally do that is almost like
I would scroll the social media all the time listening to like conference
talks, finding like new ideas and kind of solidifying that.
Now then I would maybe create a talk of that.
But what I'm now trying to do is to build this
almost in an auto generated website.
And similar to code, it has the same problem.
Like if I would just have it generate, it will be rubbish.
If I had like my own context to it, like my duration, my taste,
my harness would be saying, well, not vendors or kind of like things
or like it has to have four voices so I can put this up.
So I kind of build almost like the, the research chain.
It's not the deep research per se, but kind of curated and kind of make this
a tool that I hope is useful for people to say, like,
hey, I need to talk about the defending the ROI to my CFO.
What's the latest thinking about that?
Because there's been a few iterations,
like one is like spent through the roof and then it changes.
So kind of keeping that up to date.
And one of the other reasons was that if you do this through surveys
and you ask like what is changing in the industry, I feel that is too slow.
Yeah.
Because first of all, imagine you would do a survey now
in an organization about loop engineering.
Everybody's like what?
While there is already the
like evolution within the industry that this is where the thinking is going.
So I think it is I find it more valuable of picking
up social signals on the socials to kind of see where it's heading
and kind of start expropriating that
and consolidating that for people, everybody to access it.
Yeah. And you added it.
I think the implementation that you used to actually pull
that all together, you used the Karpathy Wiki.
It was one.
Of the things asked a whole bunch of questions
and pulled pulled data from that, which is super interesting.
And actually we can
we can take a look at the patterns cite here and from from all of that data
that you then displayed it in these, in these kind of categories of coding.
Walk us through, walk us through.
I guess the sections here that you have five sections in total.
And tell us a little bit about each. Yeah.
We one thing to note is that
this index is hand curated.
And I found that if you let it
through a bunch of socials, the naming varies
and it kind of like, you know, everybody has a different slant on it.
So I think I kind of settled into these different groups where,
you know, agentic development, everything may be more
what the solid developer is doing.
So from vibe coding, spec coding all the way up to a factory, like,
okay, what are its almost the progression as we talked about,
like when you're kind of building this out,
the first thing is you start with some prompting, oh, you got a better spec.
And I think this is also how the industry has built up
the narrative over time on how to do things more technically.
But then the second category is the platform, which I feel the more
we're heading into reusable components, whether that's context or harness
or the centralized pipeline of the dark factory,
I have a belief that that will be something provided by a platform team
or the developer experience team as a central piece,
so they have already pieces, maybe the MCP proxy
and kind of those parts, but slowly they now have a new set of things like,
you know, centralized evals for everybody, for all the teams, a registry.
So they're building up kind of those components around that.
And this feels like quite an immature section
in terms of adoption from larger organizations.
But this is very often the piece that unlocks large organizations
and helped with scaling, particularly when we think about those big questions
that people need to ask about, or how are we protecting against X?
Well, we need these guardrails.
We need these we need these policies in place.
And this is all about that kind of like distribution across a large organization.
So so this is something that we probably need to as as an industry get better at
we'll see more and more solutions.
Whereas that first category it feels like there are.
People already. Yeah exactly. That's right.
And people who are successful here in the development that that drives
the need,
the adoption and the usage across an organization,
which then mandates, well,
we need this platform to be able to support
everyone who's doing things in this agentic way.
Correct. Yeah.
So it's also the difference between
some explain it by saying there's a solo work,
a solo mode, there's a shared mode, and there's a multiplayer mode.
So you unlock a different level if you go from solo to shared
and then you know the thing.
So there's a compounding effect.
If everybody starts using the same components, there's a refinement.
So if one team kind of optimizes it, everybody has an optimization.
If you add context for those spaces now,
I think you're right in a way that it maybe is a little bit less mature.
But on the other hand, it's not like AI product.
AI inside the product is probably two years ahead
of AI coding on components.
They already have the system, they already have an observable system.
So it's not foreign to platform teams per se.
But the use case for using it for
coding is probably unique in there.
And then it has a different way for proxy how you do evals.
It's not the model it it's the coding agent.
And so there is some newness building up.
So it's almost like we need to potentially reuse
existing muscles that we already have know how to do things,
but just apply them slightly differently to the to the newer ways of working
and then quality and security.
Again, that's, that's something that is, is
is more painful as an organization as you scale out, if it's not done well
and if it's not done in a way that is, is whereby people know what they need to do.
It's similar, I guess, with writing code quality and security, it's painful
if you don't know the guardrails and the ways of working.
Talk us through this section.
So I was torn between putting quality and security in a separate section,
where on the one hand, it does belong in agentic development,
in the harness, in the specification as nonfunctional and so on.
But I found that it kind of leads a little bit of its own life.
And I would say that while agentic development
has about cranking out the code as a focus and making that code correct.
It wasn't about
verifying that it was kind of good code.
Now, harness and loop
kind of changed that a little bit, but there's still QA testing.
There's the code security.
So all the kind of nonfunctional probably belong in its category.
And I think that will lead up to
if we remove kind of the bottleneck from coding,
we solve the specification problem, which is the input.
Now we need to solve the output verification thing.
So I believe this will go on its own path.
Or maybe some of the latest trends are that after
harness has done things, it's the job of the agent to.
Convince you that it did the right thing.
So not just giving you the PR and look at the code,
but it needs to start, like helping you do that verification.
Now within evals you have an evolution as well.
So imagine you write
your code with your prompt, you have it evaluate with an LLM
as a judge.
That gives you a lot of like input and output.
Like is it correct? Or you have to look at that.
What you see the more mature people do is they build a verification
and then almost like a custom tool to deal with all the evals.
Like a fast way of saying yes no where.
I agree that it proves to you
and I expect something to happen in that quality section as well,
where there was a lot of tension between like, Will we still need an IDE?
Yes. No.
I believe the IDE for writing the code has moved into the CLI,
but is now popping up again as the review interface, which.
Is as the the ID is. Yeah, interesting.
And I think that's a move that's going to be
made where that verification and kind of that proving
it is almost like situational awareness for the user saying yes.
No. Yeah. Very interesting.
That's and why would you say why would you say that.
Is that it would go more to a, an ID interface.
Is that just because you would expect someone who is reviewing it
to want to look through the code and understand.
It might not even be the code, but the fact that they can verify
certain features of the API of the website more easily,
that there's screenshots
that there's like, you know, recordings of what the agent clicked on.
And so there's a lot more official.
Interaction.
Then you would say, like, here's a checklist in my my terminal.
Yeah, I personally still use kind of like the CLI inside of the
I'd just, you know, sometimes do reviews sometimes do that.
But I think that is the well the current evolution is
there's an orchestrator thing within the IDE.
Then there's the evolution about like jumping in when the agents are failing.
I think intent from augment is kind of doing that,
that you can step in when it fails.
And then it's like about having the review making easier.
Again, it's all extrapolations.
It's not that we have a crystal ball where the industry is going, but
but that's why I think I'm granted quality and security.
It's kind of own section as that.
I think there will be an evolution there. Yeah.
Very much.
Earlier you talked a little bit about how us humans,
the meat bags are harder to change in terms of adapting
to a new process or adapting to, to use new technology.
The last two are very, very interesting because changing roles is key.
And I think this is this is probably the hardest thing
to predict as well in terms of how we adjust will
and how fast we adjust will very much depend on what the short term
view and shape of the org should look like,
and that will be different to to something longer term.
And then scaling the org again.
How do you drive adoption through that those new roles and folks.
So let's let's talk a little bit about,
I guess, the changing roles and changing shape of the development organization.
How do you see that going. Yeah. So.
There's
obviously more of the pessimistic view of
I can't do this or we should not be using AI, okay.
That we shouldn't use AI.
That's more of a conviction that than something else, but it's not there yet.
I would typically say it is a maturity in a way that you can add more
and more rules and context and harnesses to get it in a certain way.
So one thing I would say is that a skeptical person,
get them actually to write the context and have them build the harness
right where before it felt like it doesn't work.
What can we do?
Don't use it.
But now I think we're up to a level where we can say, well,
you can make it better if you put the effort in.
So it's also one of the reasons why people are saying like, well,
we're not using it because it's not good enough,
because I haven't been working in a problem.
Now, the other problem in the industry is that they would say, well,
we like to do the coding.
We signed up for the coding, we didn't sign up for a glorified prompter
as specification, and for a while that stagnated into
Yes, we'll all become the perfect spec
writer and the code is being generated and so on.
For me, harness Engineering and loop
engineering made it click that.
That requires a technical component to be built.
So maybe the people who didn't sign up only for kind of the context
there will be working on the harness and the loops and kind of working on that.
So that kind of maybe caters for both audiences
who were okay to jump maybe more in requirements and not now
if you scale is out into a org.
The question is how many people will work on the harness.
Maybe that's a subset of all the people that we currently have
because it's a shared component.
Now, if a component gets shared, it becomes more complex.
Yeah. So there's some things.
And it was similar to that was well, you know DevOps will automate themselves
out of a job.
But on the other hand they could do things at a scale we didn't imagine before.
And then we pulled the people back.
So that is still torn.
But I think there's now a better outlet for people who still want to do
technical pieces
and kind of make sure that the agents do a good job and kind of there.
There's still a part in the review that I mentioned that they can
probably start building that review and kind of helping in that piece as well,
so that that hasn't been solidified into organizations as well.
So but that's kind of where
the roles could go as a team lead.
I think the trend is that you, instead of encouraging the solo people
to improve their own setup,
is to push them to a shared thing like, can we reuse your skills?
More skills?
Can we put like improve that, like as a team
so that driving is something I think the team lead does, but it was similar to
can we build a shared library instead of everybody inventing their own library.
And that kind of is a collaboration feature,
which I will encourage as a as a team leader to go to.
And then kind of, you know, will they become more product engineers.
That's debatable, but they have options.
They could do more product engineering.
I think at lovable, they would say 80% is working
with customers, 20% is improving the technicalities.
But I guess it's it's not for everybody in there.
So yeah.
And one of the things here
that I kind of like and maybe we'll jump into a few of these
hiring in the AI era, this is you know,
this is super interesting because what's,
what's really
kind of challenging, I guess, is what made a good developer
three years ago no longer makes a good developer today.
It's useful to have very key insights into what
good architecture, what good reliability needs mean.
We need to kind of like add into into the application or into our design.
But in order to actually be a productive engineering team
to to use AI
to the extent that we can today and look to continuously change to,
to continue using it to the to the full extent,
it feels like we need a very different type of person,
one that is very open to throwing themselves
into AI and challenging themselves to continually be better, trying
all the new cool stuff and adopting where they think it can benefit.
What would you say a good if you were to hire an engineer today?
What are the key things that you're looking for
in an engineer today that you wouldn't have said?
These would be key things five years ago. That's.
the way that phrase it is.
Somebody more as a system thinker is that architect.
Is that kind of like, you know,
they care about different things, not just about the code.
So that often qualifies probably more senior people,
but it doesn't mean that it has to be senior.
You can be a junior that is interested as well.
Probably not the person that will write
the elegant code that that is kind of
you need to have an eye for taste, but it's not the main thing.
You're be improving the system there.
And then kind of the collaborating skills and the improvement
skills that you're not there for the solar craft.
Like if somebody says like, I like language X, okay, that's great.
Are you only coming if we do this language?
Yeah okay. No.
You need to switch languages in that way.
Similar to a full stack that we define before a front end back end,
it doesn't matter.
You can navigate a bit of the different spaces.
The problem is like we used to be learning this,
maybe by having scars like step by step in our career.
So that's why it was very similar.
Again, with the DevOps, where it were like people in their 30s, 40s.
That kind of got enough from the scars, learned enough
that they were adaptable from there that we see here as well.
Picking it up.
Now, if you have two rigid ways of working, that like
that is probably not where you get hired.
But yeah, being open minded, discoverable
learning, I think the the willingness to learn
so I would typically probe is okay, how do we keep how do you keep up.
What communities are you interested in.
And if they only say their own language, their own stack, that's very limiting
there as well.
So very interesting.
And to go back to the to go back to, to.
The the patterns, I think it's that type of person
that actually when we look at scaling the org and driving adoption,
it's it's typically you don't when you look at driving adoption,
the org as you mentioned, they they mature at different rates.
And you will have teams typically that style of individual I just mentioned
you'll have a team which has probably full of those types
or has enough of that type to have a big enough momentum
that that will be the team that is on the bleeding edge.
There's always trying new things out that will learn.
Oh, these are the best ways of doing things that they can
then educate the other teams. They will get there.
The ROI that other teams will then strive for.
So let's talk about scaling the org,
how there are a ton of of enterprises that will have
or even kind of medium and large companies that will have that will want to be able
to scale their AI adoption faster than they are doing today.
What in your experience do you see is some of some of the biggest things
that are holding people back in, in the kind of area
of driving adoption that you feel they can make?
I don't wanna say easy wins because this isn't an easy
this isn't an easy thing to to adjust, right.
But that people need to focus more on in order to unlock greater adoption.
Yeah.
It's the question that I get all asked all the time,
how can I speed up my organization and just I guess there's two parts of it.
Like some parts you can't speed up.
You have to have gone through a little bit
of the prompt engineering to know, oh, I need more specifications.
I need more kind of context, I need more harness.
And so there is a learning phase to kind of understanding parts
of those components that people go through.
So all of a sudden say you're going to the dark factory.
Like people are like scrambling. They can't do that.
So that's not per se you can speed it up by giving people a formation.
Learnings.
Maybe as a team lead, you can kind of say, hey, let's start doing this
first step in there.
And I think that's where they can make
a little bit of the pace from the team where they say,
okay,
now everybody's got a fair understanding what prompting is.
Let's move and put all the context in the skills in the repo.
That's like a forcing function.
They can do that all of a sudden, oh, if we do that we need to have tests.
And I don't trust your context.
And and so
so they can pull a little bit of that pace how the team jumps to the next thing.
It's almost like an automations that unlock.
Yeah. Like you. Know they control. The sharing.
Well I think everybody's ready. Just jump.
If they don't give the signal jump, everybody will keep on doing the same way.
It's like, oh that's limiting.
Oh we're using completion. We're not using rules.
So I think there is a value in
making that cadence of learning,
like either the team or the org, like how do you jump in from solo
to more shared for like from simple practices to more fun stuff?
And when you talk about these changes, is it more important for an organization
to focus on the teams that are the most advanced,
or do you feel like there's a greater win with the majority?
Because typically, the way I look at it, you'll have an organization
where you'll have high-inertia teams, teams that don't want to change.
This is how I've done it. Get off my lawn.
You've got the very fast moving
teams, the teams that just really want to experiment
and they want to push technology as far as they can go.
They're happy to change. And then you've got the majority,
like the 80% of teams that are willing to change.
But when they see value and almost like they are led by examples,
good examples of teams that are leading a certain area.
So where would you say like an organization, an organization
can only spend, you know, it's effort effectively in certain areas.
Where would you say it's most effective for an organization to focus,
to get the best benefit longer term to, to, to improving their overall adoption?
I think regardless of whether this is how we are or like agile or any change,
as hard as it sounds,
do not spend time on the negatives in the beginning.
Find the success story.
If you can't make that work, the rest will not work.
So it's the so it's the super high.
Yeah, because they will show what it could be.
They will also show the benefits and attract
like other people trying this to get like the same benefits.
And maybe they'll look up to these people like hey, what did you do?
And so on.
If you spend time on the negatives, you're not going to get that like same thing.
So that becomes later when you have a more adoption
already, then you're like, okay, why are you still resisting?
We've offered you all the information.
We've seen skill like parts of it in the org, what is holding you back?
And that could be a variety of reasons in there. Now
it probably makes sense
is not to over rotate on one team going all the way and nobody else.
So I would say there's like a leveling up.
They spearhead the thing and then you bring others
maybe on kind of like parts of the journey already.
And then they kind of like drive kind of towards what the one team is doing.
So it's a fair assessment to say you want to make the fast teams
go as fast as they possibly can
and allow then and then the enablement is more
for the teams that are going to say, let's share
the let's share and educate them
based on the best practices that these fast teams are going.
And how can we enable you to take practices that work for your teams?
But learning from these, from these most like leading teams.
But it's a typical transformation play.
Yeah, that's the. Same hackathon I shared stuff.
I have a lunch and learn.
I share the success stories.
I celebrate, like whatever team is doing the best thing.
So that's kind of very common in kind of driving adoption.
This is DevOps, this is cloud, this is developer security.
It's all the same styles, correct? Yeah.
Now we're given all the success stories.
And that's the reason why I talk about the organizational enablement.
A lot of what happened in the organizations is that, well,
we'll get everybody the tools and some will pick it up
and they go all the way and kind of build their own future.
And, and they become very proactive.
Initially, everybody was measuring adoption
by saying, well, is everybody using a tool?
Okay.
So that's one way of saying like, okay, we have some kind of
scaling within the work.
Then people say,
well, we're going to look at like the people who go crazy on the tokens.
That's usage, right?
It's a substitute proxy kind of measurement where you say, well,
you know, the people are using more tokens.
They're like at least enthusiastic about it, but they might not be using
this quite efficiently if I were to put one measurement right now
is how much these people are contributing
to the shared components, and they're fixing the system
instead of kind of using more or having a tool.
Because if that gives the more
buildup of like people improving the shared context,
because one context improvement impacts other teams,
and that is a typically another skill from like I can be personally
very effective to this is the skill that like helps the whole org.
And that's a different measurement.
And the measurement there is.
How many touches does
the human still need to do for an agent to do the right thing.
And so kind of measuring that becomes more effective than measuring,
you know, kind of adoption just by having license counts.
And if you put that into practice you'll see like like sharing
across actually helps that metric to
because if you fix it for one, your numbers go up in all the teams.
But it's a it's I guess that's driving towards that like
more almost like autonomous factory that we're building.
But I think that is the new metric.
Who the people who contribute to that metric are the ones that are
really helping you on the journey, not the token billionaires.
Yeah, yeah. No.
I totally agree.
So a lot of the conversations that we've had here, it
kind of reminds me of some of the work that we're doing on Tessl agent, which is,
which is, you know, really maps nicely to,
to some of the ways that we that you're talking about the growth and the scaling.
First of all, if we go back to
when you were talking about creating context,
sharing that context and making that context the best it can be, I love the way
that you kind of mentioned for people who are who don't want to move
to agentic because they feel like it's not good enough, it's not where it is.
I love the fact that you say make them do a lot of work
on their skills, because that's how you actually get the most out of it.
Now, Tessl agent, of course, is an agent
that allows you to to to really make those changes.
Well, not just, you know, allowing the agent to make
those changes with your guidance, but also based on facts from logs
and pull requests that have been historically done in those projects.
So, so that that feels like a really strong way to kind of like map
Tessl agent to some of those things, but also the way that Tessl agent
doesn't try and provide you with a software factory out of the box.
What it does is it provides you with a path so that over time,
you'll get closer and closer and closer to a software factory.
So a big piece of this growing step by step and, and,
you know, optimizing as much as we can do in our context
and our skills and things like that, as valuable as that is, we need some level
of, of automation to make sure that this is being done continuously.
So so how can we what's a good process of being able to build that,
that automation of the optimization into into our daily work?
Maybe I'll first say kind of the parallel with DevOps, right?
A lot of it initially was like, okay, we deploy faster.
Can we kind of make sure it's happening?
But then the whole monitoring became observability.
And ultimately that was the feedback channel of the automation.
Like what do we need to improve.
Right.
So and I think part of what you see with the agents,
whether that's your your skills optimizer, that you can put in a loop
that makes it better, whether that's your harness tool
that detects things you're doing over and over again that could benefit
maybe from better context or becoming a script or a deterministic thing.
So kind of those feedback loops will help you scale this out,
because you can only do so much and like you contributing the system.
But if it's almost like a positive feedback loop that improves this over time
and gives you hints like what to prove, I think that's really powerful.
Now, danger of a loop is that it could be a positive and.
Negative feedback loop. Yeah.
So once a rule is accepted it could go wrong.
But that's why you need testing the regression testing also for harnesses
for anything you put in there that it's not just I edit and I pray
whether it works, but it's crucial because I often say
if you have continuous delivery and everything's
automated, and now with the I you know, another part is being automated.
The continuous learning is where the knowledge compounds
and that seems to be becoming the moat of a company.
Like how fast can you learn?
How fast can you adapt to a new idea?
How fast can you do it?
Like, even if that means rewriting the whole codebase, it doesn't matter.
But like, how fast can you get that?
And you can't do this without a feedback loop helping you to improve that.
And this is a great target
essentially to to make sure we can become as effective as we can be.
But it all comes at a cost as well, right?
And there's a section here obviously on scaling the org which is cost management.
Now last year people were just kind of like very much free to
let's try and experiment as much as we can.
Let's try and get as much usage as we can to understand what works, what doesn't.
This year, budgets are a little bit more constrained, and people are thinking more
about the return on the investment and how you manage the cost of everything
that you're doing.
Tell us a little bit about how
how important, I guess the optimizations are and this automation,
to make sure we're reading in a little bit that cost and we are getting
a return, rather than just those billionaire token users that.
Will be heroes.
I've been in the position as a VP where I had to say like, oh, look at my budget.
And the first year that AI came out,
there was no budget for AI, so where am I looking for it?
So I know it's a struggle and especially with like a lot of the vendors
raising their pricing models
or changing their pricing models that we didn't cater for, now
you can have the instant reaction, say, well,
everybody stop doing, let's remove like like reduce the budget
and kind of make sure that we we keep it in limits.
The problem then is you won't be going on that journey of learning,
because if you're limiting people, they kind of like work.
All still do it manually because I don't have enough tokens
and kind of go from there.
Now other people have kind of start assigning maybe more use cases.
So instead of saying it, the agent got better.
Now is it actually useful for that?
So I think the way you have to look at
and cost
management is, you know, I need to have a budget
for people learning and I need to have a budget
that's useful.
But the constraint of a budget should actually drive you in optimizing
that loop, because a lot of the people are blindly spending tokens.
They're using the biggest model out of things.
They are doing the same thing over and over,
where they could have been a context change or harness change.
That would save them a lot of tokens.
So if your organization is not your mature,
you feel like you're over, you know, using things.
And the parallel in the cloud was when everybody went to the cloud.
Every system was a VM.
Yeah.
And everybody's like, this is proving more costly.
And then we learn techniques to put it like on the same instance
and kind of like work from there. So I think we're in that phase.
But it's, it's very risky now for maybe a VP to say,
let's close down the full budget and kind of stop the usage,
because then your organization doesn't have that.
I think the the right reaction is, where are we open spending?
But you need to have like observability
for your FinOps, for your coding agents and so on.
So, so you need to work on the telemetry and then say, well, there's the habits.
Don't use this for that and kind of have a team work on the optimization
instead of just closing the budget of.
And let's say, you know, as a VP of engineering,
would you say, actually, of all my of all my children
or my teams, I do have preferences over where I want to spend money.
And actually the teams that are the highest performing,
the ones that are experimenting, I almost want to give them free reign,
whereas the others, I do want to make sure that they're not just, you know,
being ridiculous with their spend because we're not actually learning things
as much from them.
We're just trying to.
It is about ROI.
It's about can we do things better in a cost effective way,
whereas these other teams are actually
even if they're spending money and not doing that, we're learning, okay,
that's not a path to go, but it's money well spent.
Yeah.
And I think that's the struggle you have with the CFO, which says like,
where's the. ROI where they're.
Like they're willing to spend if there's a return.
And I think it's not per se that I would say the, you know, the best
team will get the budget, but I'll put the best team
on the most important business project to get like a return back.
And I think that's kind of the challenge is they're not always the teams,
because the biggest use case might be the more most risky use case as well.
So there's a lot of nuances to go there.
So yeah, that makes sense.
Patrick, this session has gone very fast.
I love I love these I love these chats learning from you
and for for our listeners, Tessl.io forward slash patterns.
And you can read all the wonderful research and data
as well as well as some of your takes and your your categorization there.
This is not a static site though.
This is changing over time, and there's a lot more
that I think you're planning on adding to it over time.
So, you know, absolutely.
Take a look at that site.
Very, very useful set of resources for you. Yeah.
And if you find anything missing or you have an interesting story,
I'm also very interesting to listen and learn from you.
Thanks very much.
And I hope, and I'm sure everyone at home enjoyed that session.
Extremely insightful.
Tessl.io forward slash patterns to learn more.
Thanks for tuning in and see you next time.
Bye for now. Thanks.
The AI Native Dev is brought to you by Tessl, the package manager for skills and context.
Your hosts are Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple.
Our producer is Tom Dowler.
The AI Native Dev is not just a podcast, it's a community.
And we host monthly meetups at the Tessl offices in central London.
Visit Tessl.io forward slash community to learn more and I hope to see you there.